<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- Sage and Linear Algebra Worksheets -->
<!--          Robert A. Beezer          -->
<!--  Copyright 2016 License: CC BY-SA  -->
<!--  See COPYING for more information  -->

<mathbook  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <article xml:id="overview">
        <title>Sage and Linear Algebra Worksheets</title>
        <subtitle>Overview</subtitle>

        <!-- header inclusion needs -xinclude switch on xsltproc -->
        <frontmatter>
            <xi:include href="./header.xml" />
        </frontmatter>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Introduction</title>

            <p>This is an overview, and Table of Contents, for the worksheets distributed here.  This work is licensed under a <url href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</url></p>.
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section RREF: Reduced Row-Echelon Form</title>

            <p>Construct two matrices, learning Sage syntax.  Row-reduce each.</p>

            <p>Short: 5-10 minutes, 2 exercises. [<url href="RREF/RREF.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="RREF/RREF.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section NM: Reduced Row-Echelon Form</title>

            <p>Demonstrate Definition NM, Theorem NMRRI, Definition NSM, Theorem NMUS.  Experiment with random vectors of constants.  Foreshadow the column space of a matrix.  Preliminary work with vector spaces (membership).</p>

            <p>Medium to Long: 20 minutes, 6 exercises. [<url href="NM/NM.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="NM/NM.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section SS: Spanning Sets</title>

            <p>For Section LC, I illustrate Theorem VFSLS by writing the row-reduced version of an augmented matrix with white chalk for the pivot columns (first columns of an identity matrix), white chalk for the zero rows, and then different colors for each of the remaining columns.  Then the vectors that describe the solution get the same numbers, or their negatives, in the same colors.  But first I place the <q>pattern of zeros and ones</q> in place in white.  Part of the entries in white is that they are known from just knowledge of the sets <m>D</m> and <m>F</m>.  This example gets recycled in this Sage worksheet on the following day.  This is similar to Example VFSAI.</p>

            <p>Null spaces, spans and membership round out the topics.  There is some foreshadowing of bases for subspaces.</p>

            <p>Medium: 15 minutes, 2 exercises. [<url href="SS/SS.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="SS/SS.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section MISLE: Matrix Inverses and Systems of Linear Equations</title>

            <p>A computational illustration of Theorem CINM and its proof.  A nonsingular matrix versus a singular matrix.</p>

            <p>Medium: 15 minutes, 4 exercises. [<url href="MISLE/MISLE.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="MISLE/MISLE.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section CRS: Column and Row Space</title>

            <p>A detailed demonstration of Theorem CSCS, in both directions.  You could do this quickly, or you could linger a while and drive the point home.</p>

            <p>Short to Medium: 10 minutes, 2 exercises. [<url href="CRS/CRS.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="CRS/CRS.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section FS: Four Subspaces</title>

            <p>Computations of all the constituent matrices of extended echelon form, and exercises exploring the matrices <m>J</m> and <m>L</m> for an <m>8\times 10</m> matrix.</p>

            <p>Medium: 15 minutes, 2 exercises. [<url href="FS/FS.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="FS/FS.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section B: Bases</title>

            <p>Theme: express vectors from <m>\mathbb{C}^n</m> as (unique) linear combinations of basis vectors.  Techniques include solving systems, inverting matrices, obtaining a <term>coordinatization</term> from Sage, and Theorem COB for an orthonormal basis.  The second and fourth exercises each has several parts.</p>

            <p>Long: 20-25 minutes, 4 exercises. [<url href="B/B.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="B/B.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section PDM: Properties of Determinants</title>

            <p>This worksheet is different from all the others.  It uses elementary matrices and triangular matrices to construct the LU decomposition of a <m>5\times 5</m> matrix.  It follows the logic of a constructive proof of the existence of such a decomposition, and uses some properties of determinants as checks along the way.  The conclusion discusses how to solve a linear system by first constructing an LU decomposition.  This topic is not in the textbook, though all the prequisites are.</p>

            <p>Long: 15-20 minutes, no exercises. [<url href="PDM/PDM.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="PDM/PDM.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section EE: Eigenvalues and Eigenvectors</title>

            <p>Just two exercises to experiment with, but lots of other things to demonstrate.  The theme of this worksheet is really just to show all the computational tools for various computations related to eigenvalues and eigenvectors that we would never want to do by hand.  The later sections have some impressive examples of how fast Sage can be, for both exact and numerical linear algebra.</p>

            <p>Long: 15-20 minutes, two exercises. [<url href="EE/EE.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="EE/EE.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section SD: Similarity and Diagonalization</title>

            <p>A similarity check, diagonalization of a diagonalizable matrix, an attempt to diagonalize a defective matrix, Jordan canonical form, and rational canonical form.  The two canonical forms can be skipped, they are present just to help answer the question of what is possible for a matrix that does not diagonalize.</p>

            <p>Medium: 15 minutes, four exercises. [<url href="SD/SD.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="SD/SD.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section LT: Linear Transformations</title>

            <p>Three ways to create linear transformations from <m>\mathbb{Q}^n</m> to <m>\mathbb{Q}^m</m>, in addition to basic queries and operations for Sage linear transformations.</p>

            <p>I do not present any of the four linear transformation worksheets in class, but instead suggest students work through them themselves, if they are interested.  So they are not organized with exercises.</p>

            <p>Medium: no exercises. [<url href="LT/LT.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="LT/LT.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Section ILT: Injective Linear Transformations</title>

            <p>Two linear transformations, one injective, the other non-injective.  Checks on injectiveness and kernels, along with a demonstration of the non-injective linear transformation failing the definition.</p>

            <p>Short: no exercises. [<url href="ILT/ILT.html">HTML</url>]<nbsp />[<url href="ILT/ILT.pdf">PDF</url>]</p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs>
            <xi:include href="./legal.xml" />
        </paragraphs>

    </article>
</mathbook>

